UNIVERSITY OF COLORADO SCHOOL OF MEDICINE

Drew E. Winters, PhD. drew.winters@cuanschutz.edu 317-525-3133

Biographical sketch

Drew E. Winters, PhD. is a post-doctoral fellow at the University of Colorado Anschutz Medical Campus In the department of Psychiatry under the Developmental Psychobiology and Behavior T32 program. His research focuses on brain and behavior mechanisms underlying neurocognitive and socio-affective processes in adolescents with an emphasis on adolescents with callous-unemotional traits. In this vein, this work aims to identify replicable neural mechanisms that may improve development and testing of interventions for youth with callous-unemotional traits.

Education

University of Colorado Anschutz Me - Post-Doctoral Fellow: Develo Research Group (DPRG) - Primary mentor: Dr. Joseph S	opmental Psychobiology akai, M.D.	Current	
Indiana University, Indianapolis, IN		April 2020	
Indiana University, Indianapolis, IN.		May 2016	
Purdue University, Fort Wayne, IN. − B.S.		May 2013	
Academic appointments			
University of Colorado	Post-Doctoral Fellow	2020-Present	
Indiana University	Adjunct Professor	2017-2020	
University of Michigan	Teaching Assistant	2019 & 2020	
Indiana University SOM	Research Analyst	2018-2020	
Indiana University SOM	Research Assistant	2016-2020	
Indiana University	Research Assistant	2014-2015	
Hospital, government, or other professional positions UCHealth Encompass program - Aurora, CO Therapist 2020-Present			
Family Works Inc Indianapolis, IN		2016-2020	
Rogers behavioral health – Skokie II			
rtogers senavioral nearth showe in	Benavioral incrapise	2011 2010	
Honors, special recognitions, and award	ds		
	Empirical Implications of Theoretical Models – Statistics Mastery Multilevel Modeling II: Advanced Topics		
Empirical Implications of Theoretical Models – Statistics Mastery Network Analysis II: Advanced Topics		2021	
Empirical Implications of Theoretical Models – Statistics Mastery Structural Equation Modeling with Latent Models		2018	
Developmental, Child, and Family Psychology Fellowship ICPSR Quantitative Methods of Social Research Ann Harbor, MI		2018	
Indiana University Travel Fellow		2017-2019	
Graduate Professional Student Government Fellowship		2016	
Maranda Pang Endowment		2014	
Phi Kappa Phi: Academic Honor Soc	ciety	2013	

Tau Upsilon Alpha: Human Services Academic Honor Society Hellen I. Rodney Nern Scholarship		2013 2013
Membership in professional organizations Society of Clinical Child and Adolescent Psychology Society for Social Work and Research (SSWR)		2020-current 2017-current
Major Committee and Service Responsibilities Board of Directors, National Association of Alcohol and other Drugs of Abuse Counselors, Indiana Chapter, Indianapolis, IN		2011-2018
Licensure and board certification		
<u>License</u>	<u>Certified</u>	Recertified
Licensed Social Worker – Colorado	7/2020	7/2021
Licensed Social Worker – Indiana	7/2016	8/2019
Review and referee work		
Psychophysiology	Ad hoc reviewer	2021
Journal of Drug and Alcohol Dependence	Ad hoc reviewer	2021
Neuroscience Letters	Ad hoc reviewer	2021
Journal of Juvenile Justice	Ad hoc reviewer	2018
Journal of Child and Family Studies	Ad hoc reviewer	2017
Mindfulness	Ad hoc reviewer	2016 - 2020
Invited extremural lectures presentations and	Luisiting professorships	
Invited extramural lectures, presentations and visiting professorships Winters, D.E., Affective Theory of Mind Impairments in Youth with Callous-Unemotional Traits: The Role of Cognitive Control. American College of Neuropsychopharmacology. San Juan, PR		12/2021
Winters, D.E., <i>Network typology of adolescents with callous-unemotional traits</i> . Department of Psychiatry Poster Session, University of Colorado Anschutz Medical Campus, Aurora, CO		3/2021
Winters, D.E., Adolescent Prosocial Behavior and Affective Theory of Mind: The Role of Cognitive Control and Callousness. Developmental Psychobiology Research Group, Denver, CO		3/2021
Winters, D. E., <i>Longitudinal Data Analysis Using Secondary Data</i> . S728 multivariate statistics, Dr. Sadaaki Fukui. Indiana University School of Social Work, Indianapolis, IN.		1/2021
Winters, D.E., Neural Connectivity of Empathy and its Impairments in Adolescents. Developmental Psychobiology Research Group, Denver, CO		10/2020
Winters, D.E., <i>Statistical Approaches of Propensity Score Matching</i> . Training the Indiana Department of Children Services data analysis and evaluation team, Indianapolis, IN.		3/2020
Winters, D.E., <i>Secondary data analysis</i> . S728 multivariate statistics, Dr. Sadaaki Fukui. Indiana University School of Social Work, Indianapolis, IN.		1/2020
Winters, D.E. <i>Mindfulness and Acceptance in Clinical Practice</i> . Advanced clinical prac Starnino, instructor. Indiana University Scho	etice, Dr. Vincent	6/2017

Indiana	polis.	IN.
IIIGIGIIG	POIID,	· ·

Winters, D.E. <i>Mindfulness in Addictions Treatment</i> . Presentation to staff and clients at the Life Recovery Center, Indianapolis, IN.	8/2016
Winters, D.E. Mindfulness in Clinician Self-Care and Clinical	4/2016
Practice. Presented to the staff and honor society recipients of Chi	
Eta Sigma for marriage and family therapist. Purdue University, Fort	
Wayne, IN.	

Teaching record

Indiana University School of Social Work – Teaching Assistant			
S623 Practice Research Integrative Seminar	Online	Summer 2017	
S623 Practice Research Integrative Seminar	Online	Spring 2017	
S623 Practice Research Integrative Seminar	Seminar	Fall 2016	
University of Michigan – ICPSR			
Regression Analysis II: Linear models	Online	Summer 2020	
Regression Analysis II: Linear models	Seminar	Summer 2019	
Indiana University– Adjunct Professor			
S728 Advanced Statistics – Statistics Lab	Seminar	Spring 2020	
S718 Intermediate Statistics – Statistics Lab	Seminar	Fall 2019	
S728 Advanced Statistics – Statistics Lab	Seminar	Spring 2019	
S718 Intermediate Statistics – Statistics Lab	Seminar	Fall 2018	
S517 Assessment in Mental Health & Addictions	Seminar	Summer 2018	

Grant support

Developmental Psychobiology Endowment Fund. Project title: 'The effects of cognitive load on prosocial behavior amongst early adolescents with high callous-unemotional traits and typically developing controls.' Funding amount \$7,220 Role: PI	2021-present
National Institutes of Mental Health T32MH015442-42; Laudenslager, Mark (PI), Developmental Psychopathology, Psychobiology & Behavior. <u>Role</u> : Postdoctoral Fellow	2020 - present
Indiana Department of Children Services Title IV-E Waiver A93-3-13-4F-C0-0981; Pierce, Barbra (PI), Indiana University School of Medicine. Role: Research Analyst	2019 - 2020
Indiana Department of Children Services Title IV-E Waiver A93-3-13-4F-C0-0981; Hall, Jim (PI), Indiana University School of Medicine. Role: Research Assistant	2017 - 2019

Bibliography

Published

Published Peer-Reviewed Articles

Winters, D.E., Pruitt P. J., Damoiseaux J.S, Sakai, J.T. (2021). Moderating effect of CU traits on functional connectivity underlying empathy in adolescents. *Psychiatry Research Neuroimaging*. Doi: 10.1016/j.pscychresns.2021.111429

Winters D.E., Sakai, J.T., Carston, R.M. (2021) Resting-state network topology characterizing callous-unemotional traits in adolescence. Neuroimage: Clinical,

- 2021: p. 102878.
- **Winters, D.E.,** Susan M., Hopfer, C., Sakai, J.T. (2021). Moderating effects of CU traits on transdiagnostic symptoms association with suicidality in adolescents. *Child Psychiatry and Human Development*. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10578-021-01256-w
- Winters D.E., Pruitt P. J., Fukui S., Cyders M.A., Pierce B. J., Lay K., Damoiseaux J.S. (2021). Indirect paths between functional connectivity underlying heterogenous depression symptoms in adolescents via cognitive and affective empathy. *Child Psychiatry and Human Development*. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10578-021-01242-2
- Winters, D.E., Pruit P.J., Fukui, S., Cyders, M. A., Pierce, B. J., Lay, K., Damoiseaux, J. S. (2021). Network functional connectivity underlying dissociable cognitive and affective components of empathy in adolescence. *Neuropsychologia*. 10.1016/j.neuropsychologia.2021.107832
- **Winters, D.E.**, Brandon-Friedman, R., Yepes, G., Hinkley, J. (2020). Systematic review and meta-analysis of socio-cognitive and socio-affective processes association with adolescent substance use. *Drug and Alcohol Dependence*. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2020.108479
- **Winters, D.E.**, Pierce, B. J., Imburgia, T. (2020) Concrete services usage on child placement stability: Propensity score matched effects. *Child and Youth Service Review*. DOI: 10.1016/j.childyouth.2020.105362
- **Winters, D.E.**, Wu, W., Fukui, S. (2020). Longitudinal effects of cognitive and affective empathy on adolescent substance use. *Substance Use & Misuse*, 1-7. DOI: 10.1080/10826084.2020.1717537
- Winters, D.E., Fukui, S., Leibenluft, E., Hulvershorn L.A., (2018). Improvements in Irritability with Open-Label Methylphenidate in Youth with Comorbid Attention Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder and Disruptive Mood Dysregulation Disorder. *Journal of Child and Adolescent Psychopharmacology*, 28(5): 298-305.
- Beerbower, E., **Winters, D.E.**, Kondrat, D. (2018). Bio-psycho-social-spiritual needs of adolescents and young adults with life-threatening illnesses: Implications for social work practice. *Social Work in Health Care*, 1-17. DOI: 10.1080/00981389.2018.1430091
- Winters, D.E., Beerbower, E. (2017). Mindfulness and Meditation as an Adjunctive Treatment for Adolescents Involved in the Juvenile Justice System: Is Repairing the Brain and Nervous System Possible? *Social Work in Health Care*, 1-21. Doi:10.1080/00981389.2017.1316341

Published Book Chapters

Armstrong, E., **Winters, D.E.**, Jaggers, J. (2018). Mental Health in Prison Populations. Serving the Stigmatized: Working within the Incarcerated Environment. W.T. Church and D.W. Springer, Oxford University Press.

Technical Reports for the State of Indiana

Winters, D.E., Imburgia, T., Pierce, B. J. (2017, 2018, 2019, 2020). Concrete Services Spending and outcomes for youth. Indiana Department of Child Services Child Welfare Title IV-E Waiver Demonstration Project Extension: Final Report.

Unpublished

Under Review

- **Winters, D.E.**, Sakai, J.T. (under review). Affective theory of mind impairments underlying callous-unemotional traits and the role of cognitive control: A pilot study.
- Winters, D.E., Massey, S.H., Sakai, J.T. (under review). Adolescent substance use

- outcomes in response to social consequences of use: the role of empathy.
- Winters, D.E., Sakai, J.T. (under review). Prosocial behavior limitations associated with callous-unemotional traits are moderated by internalizing symptoms
- **Winters, D. E.**, Hyde, L. W. (under review). Shared Functional Network Connectivity Between Callous-Unemotionality and both Cognitive and Affective Empathy.
- Sakai, J.T., Chintaluru, Y., Raymond, K., McWilliams, S., Carter, R., **Winters, D.E.**, Mikulich, S. (under review). Can Moral Elevation Response Increase Prosocial Behavior? Examining the Effects of Psychopathic Traits.

In preparation

- **Winters, D. E. F**unctional connectivity underlying cognitive control in relation to empathy and callous-unemotional traits.
- **Winters, D.E**. Callous-Unemotional traits association with prosocial behavior and the mediating role of cognitive control.